Life has a high tolerance for mistakes.
就是人生的容错率高着呢
Don’t worry.
别担心啊
Even if you don’t do well on the college entrance exam,
即使你在高考当中失利了啊
you might end up retaking a year,
最后可能复读了
or attending a junior college.
可能去大专了
It might not have been your first choice.
可能没有去你的第一志愿
Later on, you might have joined the military during college.
可能后来啊这个在大学阶段报国从军了啊
All of these are great options.
都是很好的选择
Or you might have chosen not to go to university.
或者你选择没有去大学
Perhaps you started a small business later on.
将来去做小生意了
Or you might have felt that there weren't many good choices for domestic schools after the college entrance exam.
或者你高考啊觉得国内的学校没有多好选择
So you went abroad on your own.
一个人出国了
In short, I want to tell you that life has a very high tolerance for mistakes.
总之我告诉你这个人生的容错率是非常的高的
One thing you should be grateful for now is
你现在应该庆幸的一件事情
You're about to turn 18.
就是你马上要成年了
Or maybe you already have.
或者你已经成年了
You're finally going to break free from your parents' control.
你终于要摆脱父母的掌控了啊
This is something I need to teach you.
这个是我需要教给你的东西
Even after getting married, many people still haven't escaped their parents' control. They haven't really broken free from their parents' influence. If your parents' control over you continues well past the age of 18, your life could become quite bleak. You shouldn't let them control you either.
就是很多人即使他结了婚了以后 他也没有脱离父母的掌控啊 如果父母对你的掌控 一直维持到18岁以后的话 你的人生就会变得非常的惨淡 你也不应该被他们所掌控啊
So, to put it this way,
所以来讲的话
If we're talking about achieving this goal,
如果你通过这个目的来讲的话
It might be a good idea to choose a school that's a bit further from home.
尽量选择离家远一点的学校也是件好事啊
But the decision should be based on your actual situation and that of your parents.
但是要根据你跟家长的实际情况来决定
How far from home should you be?
你到底是应该离家有多远
The place where you work,
工作的地方
Where you plan to settle down in the future,
将来定居的地方
And where you're currently studying, all factor into this.
现在上学的地方都是这样
But no matter what
但是无论如何
you should know that life is a vast wilderness
你要知道人生是旷野啊
a breath of the wild
旷野之息
when it comes to many aspects of life like in The Legend of Zelda
塞尔达很多来讲的话
there aren’t as many things to worry about
没有那么多去要担心的事情啊
a lot of what you face now might seem like a matter of life and death
你现在很多东西看起来是很要命的事啊
some people will pressure you to get married
有人会催你结婚
some will push you to have children
有人会催你生孩子
and others will urge you to buy a house
有人会催你买房子
Some people will urge you to buy a car
有人会催你买车
Some will push you to prepare for the civil service exam or postgraduate studies
有人会催你考公考研
Others will pressure you to do all sorts of things
有人会催你干各种各样的事
And now, some might tell you
有人现在会跟你说啊
This is the time to make a difference
这个现在就是拉开差距的时间
But back in our days, SAS
但是我们那时候SAS啊
During the SARS outbreak
搞SARS非典时期啊
I took the college entrance exam that year Actually, I scored pretty high on my first mock exam But by the time of the second mock exam, it was already the holiday season. Once the holiday started, I just let myself go. I bought a PS2,
然后我那年去参加的高考 其实我一模的时候分还挺高的 但是二模的时候呢就已经放假了 我一放假了 我这个人就放了羊了 买了个PS two
and I played it non-stop for a few months.
然后就在一直打打了几个月
Then I suddenly realized,
后来突然想到哇
there was still the college entrance exam to worry about.
还有高考这回事
In the end, I only got into a second-tier university.
结果就考了个二本啊
I didn’t do as well as I had hoped.
没有考太好
But let's go back to that.
但是咱们倒回来说
I'm just not cut out for science.
我就不适合学理科
Because my math and physics,
因为我的数学跟物理
chemistry and biology were really poor.
化学生物都非常的差啊
I should have gone for the humanities.
我应该去学文科的
Ah, that's another story.
唉这是后话
But I ended up studying humanities when I was in my late twenties.
但是我最后在二十七八岁的时候读了文科啊
I've always wanted to study acting.
我一直想学表演
I started learning acting when I was in my mid-twenties.
我在二十六七岁的时候学的表演啊
I've always wanted to learn directing.
我一直想学导演啊
I started learning when I was in my mid-twenties.
我在二十四五岁的时候学的
But all of this was after college.
但这都是在大学以后了
Actually, I attended college four times.
其实我一共念了四次大学
As you all know,
大家也知道
I'm the type who puts a lot of faith in academic credentials.
但是我就是属于那种啊迷信学历的人
But what did those credentials ultimately bring me?
但是学历最终给我带来了什么呢
Nothing more than a few wasted years of my youth,
无非就是多耗了几年青春
and a bit more money spent.
多花了点钱啊
I didn't just spend a little money
我不是一点钱花了很多钱
I wasted many years of my youth
多耗了很多年的青春
In my early twenties, I mostly spent time overseas unlike others who could still focus on their careers or even get fired so everyone has their own way of living everyone has their own path many people say when you're young you should aim to make your first fortune by 30
20多岁的时候基本都在海外度过了啊 不像别人还可以忙事业 还可以被辞职 所以来讲一个人有一个人的活法 一个人有一个人的道 很多人说年轻的时候 30岁之前没有赚到一个上市公司
I feel like I've failed in life
就觉得人生失败了
So, everyone defines success and failure differently
所以每个人在定义成功跟失败的时候不一样
I have a lot of geniuses around me
我身边有很多天才
Many of these geniuses made over a hundred million by the age of 30
很多天才30岁之前就赚了一个亿以上的啊
Some even had their companies listed on the stock market before turning 30
30岁之前就有上市公司的
There really are people like that
真有这样的人
I know a lot of people
我身边很多的人啊
They are exactly like that
他们就是这样的人
But I'm not
但我不是啊
I'm not a genius
我不是天才
I only really turned my luck around at 37
我37岁才真正意义上转了运啊
What was my life before 37?
37岁以前算什么呢
Right?
对不对
When I was in my twenties
我20多岁的时候
Wasn't I valuable in my teens?
十几岁的时候没有价值吗
No, I wasn't born 37 years old
不我不是一天一生下来就37岁了
I was definitely something
我肯定是那什么
It was only later that I became successful
后来才变得厉害
Those who become great at the age of 40
那40岁才变得厉害的人
Isn't that true for Sōun
北条早云是不是啊
Liu Bang was 48
刘邦48岁
Still watching dogs fight at 47
47岁还看狗打架呢
Only started his rebellion at 48
48岁才起兵
Right?
对不对
Early in the Northern Dynasty, also 48
北朝早年也是48
Many people say 48 is Actually a magical age, still a time to strive Everyone has a different lifespan. Speaking of the future at this point in time, When you are in your 20s or 30s, You will witness many of your classmates passing away.
就很多人说48岁 其实一个神奇的年纪还是可以拼的时候 每个人的阳寿又不一样 你将来在这个时间来讲 你将来在20岁30岁的时候 你会目睹很多同学的去世的过程
It's also possible that this process could be your own.
也有可能这个过程是你自己
But to put it another way,
但是来讲的话
I hope it won't be you.
呃希望不要是你自己吧
I wish everyone watching this video a long life.
啊就是看我这视频的人都长命百岁吧
You will come to understand life and death.
你会看透生死
So many things
很多东西
you might wonder
你就会觉得
what's the point of striving for them in my daily life?
那我平时奋斗这些东西还有什么意义呢
It seems meaningless
啊是它没有意义
The joy in life is defined by oneself
人生的这个快乐在于自己定义
Actually, what your cyber mentor said isn’t very meaningful either
其实你赛博义父说的这些东西他也没有意义
He suggested you should save money
他说的是你应该去省钱
So you can use that money to start a business
省钱了以后用这个钱去做生意
Use that money to eventually quit your job
用这个钱去让自己最终不上班
But when it comes to these things,
但是这些东西来讲的话
if your lifespan isn't that long,
如果你的寿命就没有那么高的话
why bother worrying about them?
那你还要在意这些东西干什么呢
So, while we're alive,
所以人生在世啊
a lot of things are subjective,
很多的时候东西都是自定义的
and many things are not clear to you right now,
而且很多东西你现在并看不透啊
because all you need to do is live each day to the fullest,
因为你现在只是过好每一天的时光就对了
the youth you have now, you'll dream of or recall many times in the future. The dreams I have most often now are still about being back in my senior year of high school. It's not because I did poorly on my college entrance exam.
你现在拥有的青春 你将来会多次的梦到或回忆到你 像我现在做的最多的梦还是回到高三啊 并不是因为我高考考砸了
I didn't keep regretting it for a long time.
然后我就一直后悔一段时间
Rather, that period was meaningful to me.
而是这段时间本身对我有意义啊
The time as a high school student,
作为高中生的时间
the time as a middle school student,
作为初中生的时间
were all important stages in my life.
都是我人生的重要的经历阶段啊
I've been a college student four times.
做了四次大学生啊
Being a college student four times in three countries has been a lot of fun.
在三个国家做了四次大学生也是非常快乐的
But later, I went back for further studies.
但后来我后来又去进修啊
I took additional courses at the Beijing Film Academy.
我在北电进修过
So, when it comes to that,
所以来讲的话
To be honest,
说实在的
I have six alma maters, so what’s the big deal?
我有六个大学的母校哈哈所以那又有什么呢
More skills never hurt anyone.
艺多不压身
I’m still learning now,
我现在也在学习
I’m currently studying Japanese,
我现在学习日语
and Russian.
学习俄语
Is that right?
对不对
I'm still improving my French.
还在精进我的法语
I also practice my English almost every day in this process.
我的英语也基本上也在天天在这锻炼的过程中
So it's never too old to learn.
所以活到老学到老
Why?
为什么
Because I don't have to go to work now.
因为现在不用上班了
Now I can manage my time and money freely.
我现在可以自由自备自己的时间跟金钱啊
That's the kind of state I'm in.
就是这么一种状态
So you might enter this state a bit earlier than me.
所以你有可能会早一些比我进入这种状态
Or you might reach this stage after retirement.
或者你还能晚一些
So, don’t compare your life with others. Comparison is the thief of joy. Comparison steals happiness. Life in this world for Chinese people,
到退休了以后才到我这种状态 所以说人生不要去比较比较啊 comparison is the thief of joy啊 这个比较是快乐的
is often made difficult by two things:
窃贼要把快乐就拿走了
One is the pressure of oppressive education.
中国人在人生在世啊
Actually, the two most difficult things are, uh,
其实最难受的两件事就是呃
One is the so-called pressure-cooker education.
一个就是打压式教育啊
Parents use a suppressive education style out of fear that you might become arrogant
父母打压式教育怕你骄傲
It's really scary
特别可怕啊
The second point is about comparison and competition
第二点呢来讲就是这个比较攀比啊
There's a very strong competitive mindset when comparing with others
比较啊去跟人比有竞争性的心理非常的严重
But this competitive mindset
但是这种竞争性心理来讲话
After so many years of schooling
这么多年学校教育
They will definitely instill this in you
他肯定会给你这种东西
In reality, others can get into big companies
现实当中的话就是别人能进大厂
But you can't
你进不了
Others can get into Tsinghua University
别人能上清华
but you can't. Others can get a master's degree
你上不了别人能考上研
but you can't. Others can go abroad
你考不了别人能出国
but you can't.
你出不了啊
Others have gotten married
别人结了结了婚
So when it comes to many things
所以很多事情来讲的话
but that doesn't necessarily mean they are truly happy with what they have
但是未必他拿到那些东西就真正幸福
I have been married.
我结过婚
I've been abroad.
我出过国啊
Right?
对不对
Was preparing for the postgraduate exam joyful?
我考过研快乐吗
Only the moment of getting admitted and the moment of graduation were joyful. Only the moment of getting married and the moment of getting divorced were joyful. Only the moment of leaving and the moment of returning were joyful. Many things are like thinking the grass is always greener on the other side.
只有考上那一瞬间和毕业那一瞬间快乐啊 只有结婚那一瞬间跟离婚那一瞬间快乐 只有出去那一瞬间跟回国那一瞬间快乐啊 很多东西就是这山望着那山高
So these things don't really matter.
所以这些东西就没有意义
Life is the breath of the wild.
人生是旷野之息啊
There are so many choices for free activities and actions.
真的是有很多的自由的活动行动选择的
And every experience you have in this city,
而且每一种体验你在这个城市体验
simply can't be had simultaneously in another city.
就不可能在那个城市同时体验啊
Every day is new.
每一天都是新的
Every day, in every city around the world, there are new stories.
每一天在这世界上的每一个城市都有新的故事
New things are happening.
新的东西在发生
As an important experiencer of life,
你作为人生的一种重要的体验者
you are here to experience it.
你是来这里体验的
You're not here to change the entire world.
你不是来这里改变整个世界的
You're not here to conquer everything.
你也不是来这里征服一切的
Your goal is simply to live here for a while.
你的目的就是在这儿啊活一段时间
And that's it.
然后对就完了
It's just that simple.
就是这么简单的一件事情
So don't overcomplicate it.
所以不要把它想的很复杂
People have all sorts of reasons.
是人他出于各种目的
Society has all sorts of reasons.
社会出于各种目的
They need you to do this or that.
他需要你这样需要你那样
But you don't have to do this or that.
那你也可以不这样不那样
So, there's no established practice for humans, really. There are things that must be accomplished, though. Actually, when you think about it, this world itself... The existence of civilization might be meaningless. I'm not talking about agnostics. I'm not talking about nihilists either.
所以人来讲的话并没有什么约定俗成 必须要干成的事儿 真的这世界上本身来讲的话 文明的存在都可能没有意义啊 我不是说那种不可知论者 我也不是说那种虚无主义者
But let me tell you something practical, May.
但是我跟你讲实际的may
The practical truth is that it's meaningless.
实际的东西就是没有意义
Names can be given, but true names cannot be named.
是人名可名非常名啊
People have given it meaning
人赋予了它意义
People defined this function
人定义了这个函数
People defined this event
人定义了这事件
What it means to live right
什么活着是对的
What it means to live wrong
什么活着是错的
The people around you
你身边的这些人
Your so-called mentors
你的这些所谓的师长
So-called authorities
所谓的权威
So-called experts
所谓的专家
They're all just amateur groups, really.
其实都他妈的草台班子啊
Decades ago, they themselves
他们自己几十年前
were just young people like you.
也不过是像你一样的年轻人啊
Look at the young people in their twenties now,
你看现在的20多岁年轻人
in my eyes,
在我眼里来讲
weren't they crawling around on the ground before they turned twenty?
那20多岁之前怎么满地爬呢
Right?
对不对
They were still kids.
还是孩子
Now, one by one, they're putting on suits
到现在一个个穿上西装啊
rushing to catch the subway
在赶上这个地铁啊
are they also joining the painless tide of the crowd
是不是也是进入这个无痛的人流大军
weaving through the office buildings
正在写字楼里边穿梭呢
That's right
就是这样
So you'll notice that society has a way of guiding you
所以你会发现人对社会对你有一个规劝
of setting expectations for you
对你有一个安排
of molding you through a process
有一个塑形的一个过程啊
you, as part of the education system You're also part of the crowd. So before you fully understand how this system works, you can't escape from it. Even when you think you've managed to break free one day, you might not truly be out of it.
你作为学校作为教育系统一份子 你也是普通人的一员 所以你在完完全全理解这个系统是怎么玩之前 你是跳不出来的 等你有一天你从这个系统能能跳出来 你也未必是真正的跳得出来
It's just that your mind has been liberated.
而只是你的心被解放了
Many things are like this.
好多东西就是这样
That's why in society, many people pursue different things,
所以人群当中会有很多人会追求不同的东西
power, wealth, and fame.
权利财富声望
Pursuing the meaning of life
追求人生的意义
Pursuing the wilderness
追求旷野
Pursuing poetry and distant lands
追求诗和远方
Pursuing anything is acceptable
追求什么都是可以的
But every choice comes with its own price
但是每一种东西都有自己的代价
That's just how it is
就是这样
So if life were to end after the college entrance exam
所以人生如果只是高考就结束的话
It would be too simple
那也太简单了
School teachers would definitely tell you that
学校的老师肯定会跟你这么说啊
Your parents would definitely say this to you.
你的家长肯定会跟你这么说
But what kind of life do they understand?
但是他们理解的人生又是什么样呢
Getting admitted to Tsinghua or Peking University, huh?
考上清华北大嗯
Securing a green card in the U.S., huh?
拿到美国绿卡嗯
Or getting a master’s degree, hm?
哼还是考上研究生
Or a doctoral degree.
考上博士生
Then making ten million.
再赚个1000万
Then a hundred million.
再赚个一个亿
Then a billion.
再赚个十个亿
Grow four more kidneys upon re-listing
再上市再长四个肾
Is that so?
是这样吗
What exactly is it that life gives us?
到底人生的是什么东西
True success
是真正的成功
What should be the goal of life?
人生的目标该是什么呢
To achieve this goal And then just die? What comes after achieving this goal? Are people who achieve these goals really happy? What if I set my goals a bit lower? So what if I achieve those goals?
达到这目标 然后就去死吗 达到这目标以后又是什么呢 达到这些目标的人就很快乐嘛 我把目标定的低一点又怎么样呢 所以呢达到了目标以后又怎样呢
What if I beat a game?
我打穿了一个游戏又怎样呢
What if I got 10 million when I cashed out today?
我今天撤离的时候拿了1000万又如何呢
It's just a bunch of numbers.
那不过就是一片数字
It's just something meaningless, isn't it?
那不过就是一个没有意义的东西啊
A person holds a piece of paper.
人拿着一张纸片
Holds an electronic circuit board.
拿一张电子电路板
Feeling that doing this gives it meaning.
觉得自己做这东西就有意义了
So it's actually quite effective.
所以其实是很有效的
It's really ineffective.
很很很无效的
It's a rather boring idea.
很很无聊的一种想法
In many cases,
有很多的时候来讲
our way of thinking doesn't really make much sense.
我们的自己这种思维来讲的话并没有什么意义
So let me tell you,
所以跟你说
no matter how well or poorly you perform,
无论你考得好不好
life won't come to an end.
人生都不会结束
Life will move forward at its own pace.
人生会以自己的速度去往前走
Whether you like him or not
无论你喜欢他不喜欢他来讲
your days still pass one by one
你的日子都是一天一天过的
the only thing that is fair to everyone in this world is time
这个世界上只有时间对大家是公平的
everything else is unfair
其他东西都是不公平的
there are only 24 hours in a day
时间一天就24个小时
you have 24 hours even if you're swamped
你卷也是24小时
if you spend your day like me
你一天像我这样
working late into the night still gives you 24 hours
四更也是24小时
even if you don't sleep at all
你一天不睡觉
He also has 24 hours. But as long as you don’t sleep, your body will definitely be worn out. You will be extremely tired. So, this is the time for you to enjoy life to the fullest. When you’re young, you’re bound to make mistakes. When you’re young, you’re bound to act on impulse.
他也是24小时 但你只要不睡觉 肯定身体会被拖垮 会非常的困 所以你现在应该是尽情享受人生的时候 年轻的时候肯定会犯错 年轻的时候肯定会冲动
When you’re young, you’re bound to spend a bit more.
年轻的时候肯定会花钱多一点
You can watch this video when you’re 30, it’s not too late.
你可可以到30岁再看我这视频来得及啊
It's all good
没有关系
So no matter what
所以无论如何怎么样啊
Life isn't really defined by anything
人生没有说实在是什么
Things we truly did wrong
真正做错的事情
Things that are truly worth doing
真正必须要值得去做的事情啊
Things we would regret not doing
真正不做就会后悔的事情
Life is all about self-definition
人生都是自定义的
Don't listen to all the talk from those who lived in the past
不要听那些过去的人跟你说一大堆
Look at us, we've made it to 40
你看我们这些人活到40岁了
Isn't it just like that?
不也就这样吗
Who can have lightning under their butt?
哪个人屁股底下能放闪电啊
Who can have three heads, right?
哪个人能长三个脑袋也没有啊
Right, not really.
对不也没有
Truly powerful.
神通广大啊
People of my age,
在我这个岁数的人
Some have achieved their dreams,
有人达到了自己的愿望
Some haven't achieved their dreams,
有人没达到自己的愿望
Aren't we all living like this?
不也都是这样活着吗
Is that right?
对不对
Our skin ages day by day.
皮肤啊一天天变老啊
Hair gets thinner and thinner.
毛越来越少啊
Hair grows in places where it shouldn’t.
不该长毛的地方长出毛来
Things that shouldn’t harden are gradually becoming harder.
不该硬的东西现在慢慢的硬了
Things that shouldn’t soften are gradually becoming softer.
不该软的东西现在慢慢的软了
That’s how it is.
就是这样
This is the process of aging.
这就是衰老的过程
After aging comes death, which is quite normal.
衰老完了就是死亡很正常
But can you say that all of this is meaningless? I'm not saying if I live to be 80 or 90 that it would be the same as living to be 40 or 50 the significance would be different right? So what is the meaning of life, really? No one can figure it out
但是你能说这一切是没有意义的吗 不是我要是活80岁 活90岁 那跟活四五十岁的人 那意义就不一样 对不对 所以来讲人生到底是什么意思呢 没有人能想得清楚
What does it mean to live your entire life?
你这一辈子活着来讲到底是什么意思呢
Only you can provide the answer.
只有你自己能够给出答案
So you're not living just to survive.
所以你现在不是照着死去活
You're living because you're alive.
你是因为活而活啊
I mean, how do I put it?
就是说怎么说呢
You're not living this life just to achieve a certain outcome.
你不是为了得到这个结果才过的这一辈子
Throughout your life,
你的人生当中
every moment in school,
在你学校当中的每一刻
every single second,
每一分每一秒
the friends you make will also be lost.
你交的朋友以后也会失去啊
I feel like I hardly interact with my classmates anymore.
我现在就感觉到我基本不怎么跟同学来往了
Although I still have friends,
虽然说还有朋友
most of my friends now are from my career.
但是现在更多的朋友是事业当中的朋友啊
Perhaps I’ve never had many friends to begin with,
也可能我这个人从来就没有什么朋友
so I don’t really care about these things.
所以我对这些东西也不在意
But during high school,
但是你在高中阶段
and college, you really valued your friends.
在大学阶段你还是很看重朋友的
You haven’t experienced enough betrayals from friends yet,
你还没有经历过足够多的朋友的背叛
or the mundanity that can come with friendships.
跟朋友的庸俗
Once you reach a certain point in time
因为你到了一定时间以后
you'll notice that your status has risen
你看到就是你的层次往上走了
while your friends remain in the same place and that's quite normal they might ask you for loans they might even try to steal your girlfriend or they might introduce you to potential girlfriends they'll do all sorts of things some might even contribute to your expenses Some people will cry with you
你的朋友还领到原地啊 很正常 他们会跟你借钱 他们会偷你女朋友 他们会给你介绍女朋友 他们会干很多很多事啊 有些人会给你随份子 有些人会跟你一块儿伤心流泪
but human nature often has two sides
但是人性通常就是两面
so you can't rely too much on anyone
所以你不能太过于依靠谁
Sometimes that's just how it is
有的时候就是这样
So no matter what
所以无论如何来讲的话
Life is like the breath of the wild
这人生啧他就是旷野之息嘛
You can do whatever you want
想干什么都行啊
Whatever you desire
想干什么都行
Or do nothing at all
不干事情
You can still do well without completing the main quests.
不做主线任务也一样
You can still have a great time without doing the main quests.
不做主线任务也很快乐啊
Life is like a GTA game.
人生就是个GTA
No matter how you look at it,
无论怎么样来讲的话
it’s a massive playground.
他就是个大型游乐场
Just enjoy the ride.
就好好的玩就行了
Regardless of the outcome,
无论结果是怎么样啊
when it comes to life,
人生来讲的话
the margin for error is quite high.
容错率是非常高的
You could finish junior high school
你可以初中就毕业
and then go into wholesale snacks
然后去批发零食
right?
对不对
You could finish high school
你可以高中就毕业
and then deliver food
然后去跑外卖
or you could still wholesale snacks after graduating from college
你也可以大学毕业了以后一样批发零食
deliver food
跑外卖啊
or work for a moving company
一样去做搬家公司
you might come back from studying abroad with nothing to show for it
你可能留学回来以后一事无成啊
You could stay at home all night or become a delivery person.
在家里一宿或者去当了闪送员都有可能
That’s how life goes.
人生就是这样
Life could mean that for the past 30 years or so, or even 40 years, things haven’t gone well for you, but suddenly, at 42, everything starts to fall into place. One day, you do something, and suddenly, everyone in the country knows who you are. Everyone around the world knows you. Anything is possible.
人生有可能你是过去的30几年 40几年都不顺利 突然你42岁的时候突然顺利了 突然有一天你做了什么事情 全国都知道你了 对全世界都知道你了 都是有可能
So, life is full of turning points everywhere.
所以人生到处都是转机
And whenever you step out of the door,
而且来讲你哪天出门
whenever you stay in,
哪天不出门
whoever you speak a word to,
你哪天是跟谁说了一句话
whoever might know you,
哪天可能这个人认识你
that person could completely change your life.
那个人认识你的人生就彻底的改变了啊
Marrying a different person,
嫁不同的人
marrying someone else,
娶不同的人
can also change your life.
人生也会改变
So, when it comes to many things,
所以很多东西来讲的话
there's no need to lay everything out at once,
没有必要一次性说透
no need to reveal all the secrets,
没有必要道破天机
no need to keep predicting the future,
没有必要反复的算命啊
as long as you don't seek predictions yourself,
只要自己不去算命
this thing will always remain in a superposition state,
这个东西永远都是叠加态
it's no big deal,
没有关系啊
if you're not familiar with the concept of superposition,
如果你不知道什么是叠加态的话
then just take the college entrance exam with a relaxed attitude, it's all good.
那呵呵高考就看开一点没有关系啊
Some people are destined to be scientists.
唉有些人注定是要当科学家的
Some are destined to help us develop major national projects.
有人注定就是要让我们啊开发出大国重器来了
Some are destined to be engineers.
有些人注定是要当工程师
To build bridges and connect the sea.
要架桥造海的
To create islands.
造岛的
Some are destined to be teachers.
有些人注定是要当老师的
Some are destined to be doctors.
有些人注定是要当医生的
It's all predestined.
这都是命定啊
It's a path that is inevitably taken. So your destiny is not meant for these things Why do you have to compare yourself with others Right Everyone has their own purpose in life Even if you feel useless So what
这都是必然会走的路 所以你的命定不是这些 你干嘛要跟别人去比呢 对不对 人生总有自己的作用 就算百无一用 那又怎么样呢
A scholar may be good for nothing
百无一用是书生
Right
对不对
It doesn’t matter
没有关系的
It's not that this thing is useful
并不是说这个东西有用
it has so many organs in the human body
它才那什么人体上这么多个器官
so many branches
这么多个枝节
which one is truly useful
哪个东西真正有用的
which one is truly useless
哪个东西真正没用的
who can we do without
缺了谁呢
it wouldn't be right
又不对
isn't that so
对不对
who can we do without
缺了谁
This universe isn't even complete.
这宇宙都不是完整的
So no matter what,
所以无论如何
don't overthink things,
不要去想太多东西
don't dwell on anything beyond your own existence.
不要去想自己自身存在以外的东西
Just remember that yesterday is gone for good,
你就想着昨天已经回不去了
and tomorrow hasn't arrived yet.
明天还没到来呢
Just make the most of today.
就今天就把今天过好
If you're happy today, then be happy.
今天快乐就是快乐
If you're not happy today, then that's the way it is.
今天不快乐就是不快乐啊
So it doesn’t matter
所以无所谓
Just focus on the present
只关注当下啊
Who knows if we’ll be alive tomorrow
明天活不活得到自己都不知道
So just focus on the present
所以就只关注当下啊
Live for today, as if there’s no tomorrow
今朝有酒今朝醉
It’s a simple logic
就是这么简单的一个逻辑
Enjoy your youth now
你现在享受青春
Your body is still in good shape Go out and have fun when you can Don't listen to me about saving money all the time But you should still save money when you can Just don't go overboard with spending But you should definitely enjoy life and experience it
现在身体还好 该去玩就去玩 不要听我的什么老存钱之类的 你该存钱也得存钱 你只要不疯狂的消费就行 但是该玩你得玩得体验人生啊
You should have romantic relationships
得交男女朋友
Right?
对不对
It's often the case
很多的时候都是这样
Most of life's experiences are gained in your twenties
那人生的体验都在20多岁获得
If you don't experience them in your twenties
你20多岁不去体验
When you're in your thirties and married
等你30多岁结了婚了
you'll start thinking
你就又去想哎
about doing something different
干点别的了
and go through it all over again
又等于又要体验一遍
this is called post-adolescent syndrome
这叫青春期后制
so you should seize the moment to explore when you have the chance
所以来讲该去体验的时候去体验
no matter what happens
无论怎么样
life doesn't start on the day of your college entrance exam
人生不是你高考那天才开始的
and it certainly won't end on that day either
人生也不会在你高考那天结束
No matter how the exam goes
无论考成什么样
there are always remedial options
都有补救方案
you can go to a junior college and then transfer to a bachelor's program
考大专可以专升本
and you can even change your major when you transfer
专升本还可以换个专业
right?
对不对
There's also part-time study for transferring from a junior college to a bachelor's program
还有非全日制专升本
and it won't interfere with your work
还不耽误打工啊
you can join the military
可以去当兵啊
or study abroad
还可以出国
or start your own business
还可以自己做生意
no matter what
无论怎么样
graduating from high school doesn't mean you're unintelligent
高中毕业也不算是低智商了
right?
对不对
you can do a lot of things on your own
还可以自己干很多很多事啊
if you don't know how to do something
很多东西如果你不知道该怎么干的话
come to Bilibili, go to the library
来B站去图书馆
there are many things you can do
很多东西都可以干的
no matter what
无论怎么样
life is definitely not as your parents describe it what do they have themselves? many parents themselves have a low social status earning a fixed salary so they haven't achieved much they haven't achieved much
人生绝对不是像你父母口中说的那样 他们自己怎么又有什么呢 很多人的父母自己都是社会的地位很低下 挣着一份死工资而已 所以没有什么出息啊 没有什么出息
they are just telling you a relatively safe and stable way of life
他们只是在告诉你一种相对看来比较稳妥
a more stable way to live
比较稳定的生活方法
but they are out of touch with society
但他们已经跟社会脱节了
because they are not the young people of today
因为他们不是现在的年轻人
today's young people can't even find jobs
现在的年轻人找都找不到工作都不知道呢
so it all depends on how you play your cards
所以很多东西全看你自己怎么发挥啊
there are things suitable for you to do now
现在有现在适合做的事情
I suggest you try being an internet celebrity if possible
我倒是建议大家有可能的情况下来试试做网红
give it a shot
来试试
being a content creator is actually a good thing
做自媒体其实倒是件好事
who knows
谁知道呢
maybe you'll make it
也许你就成了呢
there are many young people
也许有很多低龄的人
who have succeeded in running their own channels
其实做号要成功了的
so no matter what
所以无论如何的话
life is about trying new things
人生就去多去尝试新鲜事物就完了啊
of course, within legal boundaries
当然是要在合法的范围内多尝试新鲜事物啊
don't do anything you'll regret
不要去干一些让自己追悔莫及的事儿啊
keep that in mind
记住这一点啊
endless revenge leads nowhere
冤冤相报何时了
life is a cycle
人生总是一个循环
what happens today may not catch up with you but it might come back tomorrow no matter what live well strive to live and one day when you truly face the end of your fate
很多的时候今天不会抱在你身上 也许明天他就回来 无论怎么样的话 好好的活啊 努力的去活 然后有一天 真正到了这个自己命运的结局的时候
know why you live
也要知道要为什么而生
and why you die
为什么而死就行了啊
rather than
然后与其来讲的话
let this life pass by
这一辈子也就过去了
don't overthink it
不要想太多啊
this is a lifetime matter
这就是一辈子的事
don't put too much pressure on yourself
不要给自己太多的压力啊
the pressure of the college entrance exam is already huge
高考的压力已经够大的了
it's great that you can take the time to watch videos now
你现在能抽出时间来看视频已经不错了
or you're watching this video after the exam
或者你是在高考之后才看到这个视频
it's fine if you only stumbled upon this video now
才刷到这个视频也没有关系啊
life is self-defined
人生是自定义的
be happy
开心就得